There are a few different frameworks for writing them in Python.
They're all pretty similar.
We're going to focus on the one that comes with the standard library.
It's a pretty easy term number.
It's called unit test.
Unit test is both a framework for writing tests as well as a test runner.
It means that you can meaning that you can use it to execute your tests
and return the results as well.
In order to write unit tests using this standard library,
we need to write our test as methods within a class.
And we need to use a series of assertions that come
in this unit test library, not using the assert keyword.
OK, let's make a file here.
I'm going to call it multiply.py.
I'm just going to call it multiply.py.
Keep me firm on having more typo errors.
And I'm going to define a function here called multiply.
I'm going to take an x and a y, and it's going to return x times y.
OK, fair enough.
Now, let's write a test case for it.
Usually, these tests are in a separate file,
usually for larger projects in a separate module called tests
so that you can cleanly break them up from your code base.
But for this example, just going to put them right in this file.
So I'll say usually tests live in a test file or module.
Not in line.
And again, usually imports live at the top of the file,
but we're spending our disbelief here.
So I'm going to import the unit test library
and close my terminal there.
I'm going to import it at the top here,
because it's driving my nitpicking as crazy.
So we need to write our tests in a separate class.
And I'm going to call this class test multiply.
Calling it test multiply doesn't actually
make a unit test class.
In order to do that, we need to subclass for unit test.taskase.
That signifies that this class contains
a collection of unit tests.
Now let's write our very first unit test.
Your unit test methods need to start with test underscore
or they won't run.
They won't be picked up.
And we're going to pass in self here.
And I'm going to say the test value for x is 5
and the test value for y is 10.
And we want to use the assertions provided to us
by the unit test class here.
To find the fullest of assertions,
take a look at the Python documentation.
I'll make sure that there's a link to it in the class website.
But until then, there's a few standard ones.
And if you're using VS code,
and you're interpreter set up correctly,
you'll actually get some helpful hints here.
They all start with a serve, which is great.
If I want to test assert equal, I can even hit the...
If I call it without arguments, VS code will give me
the little pop up.
And it's going to tell me that what the arguments are
first, second, message is an optional parameter here
that we can pass in if we want to have our own custom error
message when this fails.
And we want to fail if the two objects are unequal,
as determined by the equals operator, OK?
So we're going to call multiply with our test x
and our test y.
And this should equal 50, right?
If we just have a few simple unit tests,
we don't care about having something called a test runner.
The test runner helps you discover tests and multiple directories.
So I can just say, if dendername is equal to dendermame,
put in some code in a main method here.
So if I run this multiply, or multiply,
p-i-f-o-directly, I want to call the unit test.mean method, OK?
And let's run this.
We'll see that it ran one test and the test was OK.
Let's introduce a bug into our code.
I'm going to change our multiply method to do addition instead.
Now when I run this test, or run this file that has our test in it,
it's going to say failed.
And the failures were one failure, ran one test,
and failed one test.
If I provided a custom error message here,
that optional argument should see a little bit more information there.
So we got in this search in error.
15 was not equal to 50, should be 50, right?
So this will help us catch bugs in our code.
A few important concepts here, test case,
that the class must be a subclass.
Your own test case must be a subclass
of unit test.test case.
The names of your functions must begin with test.
And because these tests usually
live in a separate test file or module, not in line,
don't forget to import the code that you want to test.
OK, so running the test, one common way of doing it,
we kind of saw, was using this triggering unit test.mean
if we're in our main context.
If you skip this part, the other way to run your unit test
is to use that Python DeshM flag.
Remember that says Python run this next thing as a module.
And you can pass in the name of unit test
along with your test file.
And it'll go and do the same thing,
even though I never said anywhere to explicitly run these tests.
When you're running your unit test with a dash em unit test,
you can also, it has to be after the dash em.
You can provide a dash V flag.
And if we look at our output now,
we'll see that our output was a lot more verbose.
Instead of saying, you know, one test failed.
Now it shows us which test it was and which class it was in.